<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<glossary>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>Glossary of terms related to pcb-fpw.</title>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>arc</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A curved trace drawn on a drawing layer.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>aperture</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>In reference to RS-274X files, an aperture is a brush shape used
        to draw things. Originally, the aperture was a physical hole of a
        specific shape and size through which light exposed a photographic
        film.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>attribute</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Varied meanings. Elements and boards may have attributes
        assigned to them, which are arbitrary mappings between a name and its
        value. pcb does not currently use those attributes itself. Within pcb
        an attribute is an arbitrary value passed between the core and the
        various HIDs, such as checkboxes and file names.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>bloat</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The most that the copper areas can be expanded before they are
        allowed to touch. For example, two 40 mil lines 10 mil apart can bloat
        up to (but not including) 5 mil before they touch, so the maximum
        bloat would be 4.99 mil.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>board</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The physical printed circuit board that is depicted by your
        layout. "Board" refers to the physical board, "layout" refers to the
        electronic data.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>clad</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A thin layer of copper attached to a thin layer of insulator.
        Once etched, the remaining copper forms the electrical connections
        described by the layout file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>clearance</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The distance beween the copper around a hole (the annulus) and
        the copper in the surrounding polygon, or between any other copper
        item (line or arc) and a surrounding polygon.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>courtyard</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The area around an element which is still "used" by the element,
        for its electrical and mechanical clearance requirements. pcb does not
        use this term, nor explicitly support a courtyard definition for
        elements.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>drawing layer</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>While designing your circuit board, pcb provides a number of
        layers to draw on. While it's convenient to think of each drawing
        layer as corresponding to one of the physical layers (copper, silk,
        etc), it's possible to group multiple drawing layers together into one
        physical layer, or assign drawing layers to purposes not corresponding
        to physical layers. For example, you could have two drawing layers
        corresponding to your ground plane copper layer, one for the ground
        plane itself and a second (differently colored) one for any signals
        that need to be routed on the ground plane layer.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>DRC</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Design Rule Check. In pcb your design is scanned and compared to
        a number of design rules, such as minimum trace thickness and spacing,
        and any violations are noted. Then, you are tortured to death with
        non-modal dialogs.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>drill file</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A computer-readable file intended to be used by automated
        drilling machines. The information includes drill diameters and
        locations. pcb may produce up to two drill files, one for plated holes
        and one for unplated holes. Automated drill machines were originally
        designed by the Excellon company, so drill files are sometimes called
        excellon files. Also called an NC drill file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>element</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>In pcb an element represents any part you might install on your
        board, such as resistors, capacitors, and integrated circuits. Note
        that this also includes anything on your board that has its own
        footprint, even if it doesn't have a part associated with it, such as
        test points, registration targets, and edge connectors. An element has
        a footprint, but is more than a footprint - it also has a reference
        designator (refdes), value, description, and location. "Footprint"
        refers to the pattern; "element" refers to the instance. For example,
        your layout might have four elements that use one footprint.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>etch resist</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Not to be confused with solder resist, etch resist is used
        during the fabrication of the copper layers to define what copper is
        removed and what copper will remain.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>excellon file</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See drill file.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>fab, fab house, fabrication house</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A company that produces (fabricates) printed circuit boards from
        mechanical design files. Most accept (or expect) gerber (RS-274X)
        format files.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>fab drawing, fabrication drawing</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A drawing that shows a mechanical overview of the board,
        including the physical outline and all physical holes. This is often
        used by fabs to sanity check their interpretation of your design
        files.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>fiducial</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A set of fiducials (typically 2, sometimes 3) can serve as a
        reference for a "Pick-and-Place" machine to accurately place parts on
        a pcb. Fiducials are free of solder mask and solder paste, as to
        provide a good contrast with the board materials to allow for proper
        optical recognition.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>footprint</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A footprint is the pattern on a circuit board to which your
        parts are attached. This includes all copper, silk, solder mask, and
        solder paste information. In other EDA programs, this may be referred
        to as a "land pattern". "Footprint" sometimes is used to refer to a
        footprint file. "Footprint" refers to the pattern; "element" refers to
        the instance in the pcb file. For example, your layout might have four
        elements that use one footprint.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>footprint file</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A file that contains a single footprint definition. Normally,
        this means it describes one element, although there are
        exceptions.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>FR4</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A specification for the insulating layer used in printed circuit
        board manufacture. FR4 is the most common grade, and is often an epoxy
        fiberglass composite.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>gEDA</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The GPL'd Electronic Design Automation suite of tools. See
        http://www.geda.seul.org. It includes, among other things, the gschem
        schematic editor, which produces input that pcb can use.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>gerber, gerber file</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The common name for an RS-274X formatted file. Originally named
        after the Gerber Photoplotter Company.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>gschem</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The schematic editor that comes with gEDA.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>keepout</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A region created by the designer solely to prevent something
        else from existing there. For example, an element with a copper
        keepout would prevent the autorouter from routing traces through that
        area. pcb does not currently support keepouts.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>landpattern</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See footprint.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>layer</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>There are two meanings of "layer'' in pcb. See "drawing layer"
        and "physical layer".</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>layout</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The board design information depicted by the edits you've made;
        this is what's stored in a pcb file and displayed on the screen.
        "Board" refers to the physical board, "layout" refers to the
        electronic data.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>line</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A straight segment drawn on a drawing layer.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>mark</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Normally, pcb reports coordinates relative to the origin (upper
        left) of the board. However, you can designate a location on the board
        such that pcb also reports coordinates relative to that location. Such
        a location is the mark, and is drawn with an X shape. Elements also
        have a mark; this is the local origin from which other locations
        within the element are measured. Element marks are drawn as small
        diamonds.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>mask</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See "solder mask".</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>mil</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A mil is 0.001 inch, or a "milli-inch". Other packages may call
        it a "thou", short for a thousandth of an inch (25.4 mm / 1000 =
        0.0254 mm).</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>NC drill</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Numerically Controlled Drill file. See "drill file".</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>negative layer, negative plane</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>For most drawing layers, the stuff you draw corresponds to stuff
        that exists in a physical layer. For example, trace drawn on a copper
        layer results in copper existing on the board. For negative layers,
        however, what you draw results in what does <emphasis
        role="bold">not</emphasis> exist on the board. The solder mask gerber,
        for example, is such a layer - a circle drawn in the solder mask
        gerber results in a hole in the physical solder mask. pcb represents
        such layers in a meaningful way on the screen, but exporters may use a
        negative layer according to the needs of the fabrication
        process.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>netlist</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A list of symbolic electrical connections, normally provided as
        input to pcb from a schematic layout program, which represents the
        desired electrical connectivity of the board. pcb can compare the
        desired (loaded) netlist with the actual (copper) netlist and advise
        you of shorts or unrouted connections. If there are unrouted
        connections, it can use those to create a rat's nest to assist you in
        routing them.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>outline</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The physical shape and dimension of your physical board. By
        default, this is a rectangle the size of your working area (the "board
        size"), but if you name one of the drawing layers "outline" that is
        used instead. While your board is itself a polygon shape, a polygon
        drawing object is not used to denote its outline - by convention, 10
        mil (0.254 mm) wide lines are used to draw the outline, and the
        centerlines of those lines indicate the actual outline edges.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>package</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>An electronic component can be packaged in one or more discrete
        forms, this is called a package.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>pad</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>An electrical connection to an element which does not require a
        through hole, for example as used by a surface mounted device.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>part</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A basic electronic element usually packaged in a discrete form
        with two or more connecting leads or metallic pads. Parts are intended
        to be connected together, usually by soldering to a printed circuit
        board, to create an electronic circuit with a particular
        function.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>paste</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See "solder paste".</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>paste stencil</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A thin sheet, usually plastic or metal and 0.002 to 0.005 inches
        thick, with holes where solder paste should be applied to your
        board.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>pcb file</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A file used by pcb to store board layout. Such files end in
        ".pcb" and are normally readable (and editable) text files.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>pcb units</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Internally, pcb maintains all measurements in its own units,
        typically with nanometer (nm) resolution, which is much smaller than
        both mils and millimeters. These are the default units used in pcb
        files. At the time this text was written. pcb-fpw stil uses units that
        are 1/100 of a mil, and pcb parses these as the old "no-units file
        format" units.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>physical layer</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>In the manufacture of circuit boards, a physical layer is, for
        example, each layer of copper, each side's silkscreen, the solder
        mask, the paste stencil, the physical outline, etc. Each physical
        layer requires a single layer definition to be produced by pcb; for
        professional fabs there is one gerber file for each physical
        layer.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>pin</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>An electrical connection to an element which requires a through
        hole, for example as needed by a DIP socket. Contrast with a pad. Note
        that pins and vias are mechanically identical, although pins default
        to untented while vias default to tented.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>plated hole, plated through hole, PTH</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>During fabrication, some holes become coated with copper which
        connects all the copper layers together at that point. Since this is
        normally done by electroplating, such holes are called "plated" holes,
        and normally have a copper annulus around them.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>polygon</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A polygon defines the ouline of a drawn region on a drawing
        layer. When used on a drawing layer representing a copper physical
        layer, it causes a copper polygon to exist in the final board, for
        example. Unlike lines and arcs, a polygon does not have a "thickness"
        as the lines define the exact boundary of the shape.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>rectangle</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A special case of a polygon.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>resist</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>In pcb this usually means the etch resist.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>RS-274D, RS-274X</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A file format used originally by photoplotters, but now used by
        any machine used to fabricate circuit boards. The D variant requires a
        separate file defining all the apertures, and is considered obsolete.
        The X variant is newer and includes the aperture definitions. Since
        these formats were defined by the Gerber Photoplotter company, they
        are commonly known as "gerber files". Although there is no "owner" of
        the RS-274X spec, it can be found at various places online such as
        "http://www.artwork.com/gerber/274x/rs274xrevd_e.pdf".</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>shrink</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>The most that a copper area can decrease in size before it no
        longer touches (overlaps) an adjacent copper area.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>silk, silkscreen</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A layer of ink or pigment drawn on the circuit board (usually,
        one for each side of the board) in order to include, for example, part
        numbers or element outlines.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>soldermask</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A layer of heat resistant film placed over the outermost copper
        layers of your board, to prevent solder from sticking to any covered
        copper. When used to cover traces routed between pins or pads, this
        can help avoid shorts to those traces. Note that when shown in pcb the
        mask is drawn where the film exists, but when output (to postscript or
        gerber, for example), it is often "drawn" where the mask is to be
        removed.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>solder resist</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See soldermask.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>solder paste</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Ground up solder mixed with flux. This paste is normally
        squeegeed through a paste stencil to deposit a measured amount of
        paste on each pad on the board. Once the paste is applied, parts can
        be positioned on the paste, and the board heated - which melts the
        paste and solders the parts to the board.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>tented</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>When a circuit board is made with a solder mask, you have the
        option of opening a hole in the mask over vias, or leaving the solder
        mask intact over them. A via with an intact solder mask over it is
        tented, as the solder mask acts like a tent over the copper and
        hole.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>thermal, thermal relief</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Since copper is an efficient heat sink, connections to a large
        region of copper would be very difficult to solder - the copper heat
        sink prevents you from adequately heating the connection. To fix this,
        small cutouts are made around each such connection to create a thermal
        barrier, so that heat applied to the connection stays at the
        connection. Such a set of cutouts, and the copper bridges that remain,
        is called a "thermal". Thermals come in many patterns, which allows
        the designer to ensure adequate electrical connectivity and/or
        manufacturability.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>thickness</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>In pcb this often refers to the width of a line or arc, not the
        thickness of the copper film used to produce the board. This is also
        the "size" of a line or arc.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>thou</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>See "mil".</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>toner transfer, TT</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A home-fabrication method that involves printing a layer with a
        laser printer, and transferring the toner from that print to an
        unetched copper board. The toner acts as an etch resist.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>trace</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>Any copper added to a copper layer whose purpose is to connect
        electrical signals between elements. Traces may be built up from
        lines, arcs, and polygons.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>unplated hole</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>During fabrication, some holes are drilled after electroplating,
        and so do not receive the copper that would otherwise connect layers.
        Such holes are unplated holes, and normally do not have a copper
        annulus around them either.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>untented</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>When a hole is placed in the solder mask in order to expose a
        via below it, such a via is untented. Untented vias are available as
        test points or places to add wires later.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>via</glossterm>

      <glossdef>
        <para>A via is a connection between different copper layers. In pcb
        all vias are "through" vias, in that they connect copper on all
        layers.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
</glossary>
